Chaloner Prize Foundation
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Chaloner Prize Foundation records
1915-1974
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Chaloner Prize Foundation
4.0 linear feet
The records of Chaloner Prize Foundation measure 4.0 linear feet and date from 1915 to 1974. The records consist of the files of the two Secretaries, George F. Lewis and S. LeRoy French, and four of the Trustees, Charles Platt, William Rand, Olin Dows, and William Platt. Included within these records are correspondence, lists, files on award recipients, and three scrapbooks maintained by Dows. Also found within the collection are legal records, printed material, and financial records.
Provenance
The collection was donated in 1982 by the American Academy in Rome, along with their records. During the processing of the Academy's records, it was determined that the Chaloner Prize Foundation records were a separate entity, and the collection was separated from the Academy records.
Related Material
Also available at the Archives of American Art are the American Academy in Rome Records, 1855-circa 1981.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 5664-5669 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Historical Note
The Chaloner Prize Foundation was founded in 1890 by John Armstrong Chaloner in New York, NY, for the purpose of granting awards to individual artists for study of art in Paris. Initially known as the "Paris Prize Fund," held by the United States Trust Company of New York, the fund relied on contributions from art patrons such as Henry and Arthur Astor Carey. Due to personal troubles Chaloner could not manage the account and passed power of attorney to others. By 1917 the Trust had made only two grants. That year Chaloner brough suit against Bankers Trust Company and "others" in order to incorporate the foundation. The subsequent legal judgement by the New York State Supreme Court created the grant-administering institution.
Following the 1917 reorganization, the Foundation's first award for Paris Prize was $4,800 plus travel expenses to John Ferris Connah for five years (1921-1926). Subsequent awards were $6,000 with grantees selected every other year. With the beginning of World War II, Europe was not longer a secure place for visiting artists, and the 1939 and 1940 award recipients studied in Mexico. No further grants were given until 1948.
Lawton S. Parker, Charles A. Platt, and William Rand, Jr. were appointed to the first board of trustees. George F. Lewis was appointed as Foundation clerk. He maintained correspondence, set up board meetings, and communicated with artists as needed. When Charles Platt and William Rand, Jr. died in the early 1930s, they were succeeded by their sons, William Platt and Robert Rand. Shortly after Lewis resigned in 1938, S. LeRoy French secretary.
In 1969 national legislation regarding tax-exempt foundations made the future increasingly uncertain for trusts like the Chaloner Prize Foundation. In 1973 a final grant was made to the American Academy in Rome to be used for a fellowship in sculpture. In 1974 the foundation was dissolved and all assets and records were transferred to the American Academy in Rome.
Scope and Content Note
The records of Chaloner Prize Foundation measure 4.0 linear feet and date from 1915 to 1974. The records consist of the files of the two Secretaries, George F. Lewis and S. LeRoy French, and four of the Trustees, Charles Platt, William Rand, Olin Dows, and William Platt. Included within these records are correspondence, lists, files on award recipients, and three scrapbooks maintained by Dows. Also found within the collection are legal records, printed material, and financial records.
The Secretaries' Files contain backgroundpapers and photographs of John Chaloner's home in Virginia. Early correspondence includes letters from John Chaloner to Foundation officials on a variety of issues concerning his personal history and legal battles, personal perceptions regarding jurying and applicants, as well as observations about award amounts and duration of grants. Correspondence informed trustees of business transactions, legal matters, and awardee activities. Also found in this series are examples of competition circulars for other organizations, distribution lists, and rough drafts for the Paris Prize announcements.
Trustees' files are composed primarily of the records of William Platt, but include earlier minutes and bylaws. Within the correspondence are letters and telegrams to awardees. Of particular note are scrapbooks compiled by Trustee Olin Dows on the history of grants, covering activities between 1917 and 1960. A few correspondence files from Lawton Parker, Charles Platt and William and Robert Rand can be found here as well.
Legal records document the New York Supreme Court Judgment of 1917 and the transfer of assets to the American Academy in Rome. Printed material includes a poster; applications, notices, regulations and conditions for prizes; booklets on the activities of the Foundation; and information from other artist organizations. Financial records contain documentation on early expenses and income; receipts and transmittals; and scattered financial holdings statements.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as # series:
Series 1: Secretaries' Files, 1916-1974 (Box 1-2; 1.6 linear feet)
Series 2: Trustees' Files, 1915-1974 (Box 2-4; 1.6)
Series 3: Legal Records, 1917-1974 (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1919-1971 (Box 4; 8 folders)
Series 5: Financial Records, 1917-1967 (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art--Competitions; Art--Scholarships, fellowships, etc
Types of Materials:
Drafts (documents); Legal records; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Names:
Dows, Olin, 1904-; Chaloner, John Armstrong; French, S. LeRoy; Lewis, George F.; Parker, Lawton, 1868-1954; Platt, Charles A. (Charles Adams), 1861-1933; Platt, William, 1897-1984; Rand, Robert; Rand, William
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Secretaries' Files, 1916-1974, Series 1:; (Box 1-2; 1.6 linear feet)
  Files of George F. Lewis, includes correspondence with John Chaloner regarding a variety of issues concerning his personal history, legal battles, jurying, applicants, award amounts and duration of grants; with trustees, informing them of business transactions, legal matters, and awardee activities, with awardess; and with Guillaume Lerolle, artists' representative in Rome, as well as preparatory promotional materials. S. Leroy French's files consist of general correspondence, correspondence with Lord, Day and Lord, 1973; requests of information and applications; and correspondence with awardees. Also found in the Secretaries files are background papers and photographs of John Chaloner's home in Cobham, Virginia.
  - Background Papers, 1916-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of John Chaloner's Home in Virginia, 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Records of George F. Lewis (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1917-1937, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
    - Examples of Competition Circulars and Drafts for Announcement of Paris Prize, 1918-1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Distributions List, Undated, 1926-1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Records of S. LeRoy French (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1946-1973, (14 folders) (Box 1, Folder 11-24)
    - Correspondence, Lord, Day & Lord (lawfirm), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence regarding Merger with American Academy in Rome, 1970-1974, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Correspondence regarding Grant Award Publications, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, Requests for Applications, 1941-1953, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 29-32)
    - Correspondence, Requests for Applications, 1954-1970, (8 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Judith A. Allen Efstathion, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Prisilla Bowden, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Nancy Lee Forte, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Paul Giovanopalos, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Robert Irwin, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Erle L. Johnson, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Anne Martin, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, John A. Matt, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Barbara Nordberg, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Richard H. Rappaport, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Frank George Roth, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Claudia Lorraine Widdiss, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Wayne Francis Williams, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Kenneth R. Worley, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Preliminary Promotional Materials, 12th Competition, 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Lists of Trustees, circa 1957 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Form Letters, 1958-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Files in Storage, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Trustees' Files, 1915-1974, Series 2:; (Box 2-4; 1.6)
  Trustees' files contain by-laws and minutes; correspondence of Charles Platt, William Rand, Olin Dows, William Platt, and Robert Rand; and files on applicants awarded, considered, and withdrawn. The Olin Dows files also contain three scrapbooks which he compiled in the 1950s on the history of the Chaloner Prize Foundation, and some financial records, notes, correspondence, and printed material. Applications Awarded files may overlap with files maintained by the Secretaries in Series 1.
  - Bylaws, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Minutes, 1917-1970, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 28-31)
  - Minutes, 1923-1969 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Minutes, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Charles Platt, Correspondence, 1915-1922 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - William Rand, Correspondence, 1917-1928 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Robert Rand, Correspondence, 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Records of Olin Dows (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "Data Collected for Olin Dows," Financial Records and Histories, 1956- 1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Data Collected for Olin Dows," Foundation Letters and Printed Matter, 1919- 1935, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Data Collected for Olin Dows," Notes, Correspondence, and Summaries, 1957-1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Scrapbook Vol. 1, 1917-1922 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Scrapbook Vol. 2, 1933-1956 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Scrapbook Vol. 3, 1956-1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Records of William Platt (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, General, 1935-1959, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - Correspondence, General, 1965-1974, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
    - Correspondence, Lewis Iselin, Jr., 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, Lord, Day, & Lord, 1970-1974, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
    - Paris Prize, Awardee Lists, 1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Paris Prize, Applications Withdrawn, 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Judith Allen (Efstathiou), 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Priscilla Bowden, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Henri Brenner, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, John Ferris Connah, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Philip Clarkson Elliot, 1928-1930 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Herbert Fink, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Nancy Lee Fort, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Paul Giovanopoulas, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Robert Irwin, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Erle Loran Johnson, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Michael Lenson, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Anne Martin, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, John A. Matt, 1962, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Barbara Nordberg, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Eleanor Platt, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Richard H. Rappaport, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Frank Roth, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Daniel Snyder, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Martina Steere (Hoffman), 1924-1934 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Frede Vidar, 1935-1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Claudia Widdiss, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Wayne Williams, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Paris Prize Awardee, Kenneth Worley, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Paris Prize, Applications Considered, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Paris Prize, Application Considered, Samuel Brecher, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Paris Prize, Application Considered, Arnold T. Grindon (de Grendon), 1931- 1932 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Paris Prize, Application Considered, Osvaldo Louis Gugliemi, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Paris Prize, Application Considered, Nathan Hoffman, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Paris Prize, Application Considered, Paul Raphael Meltsner, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Paris Prize, Application Considered, Anatde Shulkin, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Paris Prize, Application Considered, Maxwell B. Starr, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Paris Prize, Application Considered, Alfred J. Wands, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Paris Prize, Application Considered, Robert E. Weaver, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Legal Records, 1917-1974, Series 3:; (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
  Legal files primarily document the U.S. Supreme Court Judgement, 1917, and the transfer of the Foundation's assets to the American Academy in Rome.
  - U.S. Supreme Court Decision, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - New York Supreme Court Decision, 1917, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
  - Bonds, Accounts, and Appointments, 1923-1959, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 27-29)
  - Tax Exemptions, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Complaint Regarding Grantee Travel and Investments, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - New York Supreme Court Settlement, Trustee Accounts, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - New York Supreme Court Settlement, Petition, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - New York Supreme Court Settlement, Receipts, Release and Supplemental Accounts, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - New York Supreme Court Settlement, 2nd Supplemental Account, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - New York Supreme Court Settlement, Trustee Accounts, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Printed Material, 1919-1971, Series 4:; (Box 4; 8 folders)
  Printed material includes a comprehensive selection of items published by the Chaloner Prize Foundation in the early 1920s, a few foundation materials up to 1971 and miscellaneous booklets published by other organizations.
  - Applications, Notices, Regulations, and Conditions for Prizes, 1921-1971, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
  - Annoucement Poster, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Booklets Reporting the Prize Winners, 1919-1923 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Proof and Draft for Booklet, 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Press Clippings, 1927-1970 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Publications from other Artist Organizations, 1919-1920, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Report on American Foundations and their Fields, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Financial Records, 1917-1967, Series 5:; (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
  This series includes journal and ledger postings of early income and expenses, some detailed information regarding transmittals of stipends to artists, and some financial holdings statements. Additional holdings statements are found in the correspondence of the Secretary and the Trustees.
  - Journal (Posting of Expenses), 1917-1938 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Ledger (Posting of Income), 1917-1937 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Receipts and Transmittals (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Lists, 1917-1937 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - American Express Co., 1927-1929 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Chase National Bank, 1930-1937 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Equitable Trust of NY, 1922-1930 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - John Munroe & Co., 1924-1927 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous, 1928-1937 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - National Academy of Design, 1920-1924 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1920-1937 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Co., 1940 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Societe du Gazde Paris, 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - United States Fidelity and Guaranty Co., 1917-1937 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Financial Holding Statements, 1954-1967, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 58-59)